MANAS KHATUA

CONTACT Information

Present Address:

Postdoctoral Research Fellow, ISTD Pillar Singapore University of Technology & Design 8 Somapah Road, Singapore - 487372 E-mail: manas_khatua@sutd.edu.sg URL: http://manaskhatua.github.io/

Mob. +65 83452911

Permanent Address:

C/o - Bijoy Kr. Khatua Vill. & P.O. - Bahurupa P.S. - Narayangarh Dist. - Paschim Medinipur

West Bengal, India - 721437 E-mail: manaskhatua@gmail.com

PH.D. RESEARCH WORKS My Ph.D. thesis work is "Analysis of Collisions in Contention-Based Wireless Networks", specifically in Wireless LANs. That work focuses on analyzing the different aspects of frame collision in wireless MAC protocol design. In response, we analyze the theoretical performance of the DCF MAC protocol from the packet-centric viewpoint, followed by the design and analysis of performance tuning mechanisms of the IEEE 802.11 DCF and the IEEE 802.11e EDCA protocols. We further analyze and design a scheme for detecting jamming, one of the causes of frame collision, in an energy constrained network.

RESEARCH Interest

- Wireless LANs
- Wireless Network Security
- Wireless Ad-hoc & Sensor Networks
- Mobile Cloud Computing
- Machine Learning

EDUCATION

Ph.D. (Provision certificate awarded: Sept. 2015)

Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur

Thesis: Analysis of Collisions in Contention-Based Wireless Networks

Adviser: Dr. Sudip Misra

Research Area: Wireless Networks

M. Tech. in Information Technology, 2007

Bengal Engineering and Science University, Shibpur

Thesis: GSPIN: Gradient-based Sensor Protocol for Information via Negotiation

in Wireless Sensor Network Adviser: Dr. Indrajit Banerjee

Area of Study: Wireless Sensor Network

Marks: 9.2/10

B. Tech. in Computer Science & Engineering, 2003

University of Kalyani

College: RCC Institute of Information Technology, Kolkata.

Project: Design and Implementation of an Inventory Control System

Adviser: A. K. Chandra, Regional Computer Centre, Kolkata

Marks: 75.06%

Higher Secondary in Pure Science, 1998

West Bengal Council of Higher Secondary Education

School: Narayangarh R. R. C. L. U. S. Niketan, West Bengal.

Marks: 74.40%

Secondary, 1996

West Bengal Board of Secondary Education

School: Narayangarh R. R. C. L. U. S. Niketan, West Bengal.

Marks: 77.77%

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, India

Teaching Assistant, School of Information Technology

- Wireless Ad-Hoc & Sensor Networks, Autumn Semester 2012.
- Information System Design Laboratory, Autumn Semester 2011.

Dr. B. C. Roy Engineering College, Durgapur, India

Sr. Lecturer, Department of Information Technology, 1^{st} January, 2008 to 5^{th} February, 2008.

Taught: Data Structure

Bankura Unnayani Institute of Engineering, Bankura, India

Lecturer, Department of Computer Science & Engineering, 22^{nd} November, 2005 to 31^{st} December, 2007.

Taught: C Programming, JAVA, Operating Systems, Data Structure

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Temasek Laboratories, SUTD, Singapore

Research Assistant (19th May, 2015 to 10th September, 2015)

 $Postdoctoral\ Research\ Fellow\ (11^{th}\ September,\ 2015\ to\ Till\ Date)$

- Project: Cross-functional Information System for Decision Making (CISDeM)
- Sponsor: Ministry of Defence, Singapore.
- Type of Research: CISDeM is a cyber-information research program for decision making against network security threats. It adopts an interdisciplinary research view spanning security, natural language processing, machine learning, signal processing, and networking to protect missioncritical network infrastructures.

Sponsored Research and Industrial Consultancy, IIT Kharagpur, India

Senior Research Fellow (26th May, 2010 to 31st March, 2013)

- Project: Towards Robust Efficient and Secure Data Acquisition in Underwater Sensor Networks.
- Sponsor: Department of Information Technology, Government of India.
- Type of Research: Protocol design in UWSNs for a) Delay Tolerant Routing, b) Fault Tolerant Routing, c) Jamming Detection, and d) Robust Architecture. UWSN simulator design using MATLAB and NS3.

Professional EXPERIENCE

Tata Consultancy Services, India

Assistant Systems Engineer, Banking & Financial Services 6^{th} February, 2008 to 25^{th} June, 2010.

- Provided the core Insurance Solution using TCS B α NCS Insurance.
 - Client: DLF Pramerica Life Insurance Company Limited, India. Duration: April, 2009 to June, 2010.

Role: System Designer, Developer, and Development Team Leader

• Client: Skandia-BSAM Life Insurance Company Limited, China. Duration: June, 2008 to March, 2009. Role: System Developer.

PRESENTATION AND TALKS

- Delivered guest lecture on "Recent Research Trends in Wireless Sensor Networks" in "Seminar on Computing and Informatics", organized by St. Thomas' College of Engineering and Technology, Kolkata, June 2013.
- Presented my paper in the 14th International Conference on Distributed Computing and Networking, TIFR, Mumbai, January 3-6, 2013,

AWARDS

National Internet Exchange of India

• National Scholarship at Ph.D. level for one year, 2014-15.

Professional AFFILIATIONS

- IEEE Student Member since January 2013 (ID: 92558724)
- Member of Narayangarh Vivekananda Yuva Mahamandal, an affiliated unit of Akhil Bharat Vivekananda Yuva Mahamandal, since 1989.

REVIEW SERVICE • IHCI 2012, TechSym 2014,2016, INDOCRYPT 2014, VTC 2016

IEEE Transactions on Cloud Computing

IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology

IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing

Journal of Network and Computer Applications

EURASIP Journal on Wireless Communications and Networking

Photonic Network Communications

International Journal of Communication Networks and Distributed Systems

Journal **Publications**

- S. Misra and M. Khatua, "Packet-Centric Trade-off and Unfair Success Region in IEEE 802.11 WLANs," *IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology*, (Accepted on July 2016, Paper ID: VT-2016-00213.R1).
- M. Khatua and S. Misra, "D2D: Delay-aware Distributed Dynamic Adaptation of Contention Window in Wireless Networks," *IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing*, Vol. 15, No. 2, pp. 322-335, February, 2016.
- S. Das, M. Khatua, S. Misra and M. S. Obaidat, "Quality-assured Secured Load Sharing in Mobile Cloud Networking Environment," *IEEE Transactions* on Cloud Computing, (Accepted on July 2015, Paper ID: TCCSI-2014-11-0554.R2).
- S. Misra, S. Singh and M. Khatua, "MIRACLE: Mobility Prediction Inside a Coverage Hole Using Stochastic Learning Weak Estimator," *IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics*, (Accepted on June 2015, Paper ID: CYB-E-2015-02-0205.R1).
- S. Misra and M. Khatua, "Semi-Distributed Backoff: Collision-Aware Migration from Random to Deterministic Backoff," *IEEE Transactions* on *Mobile Computing*, Vol. 14, No. 5, pp. 1071-1084, May, 2015.
- S. Misra, S. Mishra and M. Khatua, "Social Sensing-based Duty Cycle Management for Monitoring Rare Events in Wireless Sensor Networks," IET Wireless Sensor Systems, Vol. 5, No. 2, pp. 68-75, April, 2015.
- S. Misra, S. Singh, M. Khatua and M. S. Obaidat, "Extracting Mobility Pattern from Target Trajectory in Wireless Sensor Networks," *International Journal of Communication Systems*, Vol. 28, No. 2, pp. 213-230, January, 2015.
- 8. M. Khatua and S. Misra, "CURD: Controllable Reactive Jamming Detection in Underwater Sensor Networks," *Pervasive and Mobile Computing*, Vol. 13, pp. 203-220, August, 2014.
- S. Misra, S. Das, M. Khatua and M. S. Obaidat, "QoS-Guaranteed Bandwidth Shifting and Redistribution in Mobile Cloud Environment," *IEEE Transactions on Cloud Computing*, Vol. 2, No. 2, pp. 181-193, April-June, 2014.
- T. Ojha, M. Khatua and S. Misra, "Tic-Tac-Toe-Arch: A Self-organizing Virtual Architecture for Underwater Sensor Networks," *IET Wireless* Sensor Systems, Vol. 3, No. 4, pp. 307-316, December, 2013.
- S. Misra, S. Dash, M. Khatua, A. V. Vasilakos and M. S. Obaidat, "Jamming in Underwater Sensor Networks: Detection and Mitigation," *IET Communications*, Vol 6, No. 14, pp. 2178-2188, September, 2012.

Conference Publications

 M. Khatua and S. Misra, "Exploiting Partial-Packet Information for Reactive Jamming Detection: Studies in UWSN Environment," Proc. of the 14th International Conference on Distributed Computing and Networking, TIFR, Mumbai, January 3-6, 2013, pp. 118-132.

- 2. S. Das, S. Misra, M. Khatua and Joel J. P. C. Rodrigues, "Mapping of Sensor Nodes with Servers in a Mobile Health-Cloud Environment," *Proc.* of the 15th International Conference on E-Health Networking, Application and Services, Lisbon, October 9-12, 2013, pp. 481-485.
- S. Misra, A. Mondal, S. Banik, M. Khatua, S. Bera and M. S. Obaidat, "Residential Energy Management in Smart Grid: A Markov Decision Process-Based Approach," Proc. of the IEEE International Conference on Internet of Things, Beijing, August 20-23, 2013, pp. 1152-1157.

OTHER PUBLICATIONS

 M. Khatua and S. Misra, "Realizing Virtual MIMO through Opportunistic Parallelism for Increasing Revenue in Enterprise Wireless Local Area Networks." In: The Second IDRBT Doctoral Colloquium, IDRBT, Hyderabad, December 20-21, 2012.

BOOK CHAPTERS

 S. Misra and M. Khatua, "Cross-Layer Techniques and Applications in Wireless Sensor Networks," In: H. F. Rashvand and Y. S. Kavian (Eds.), Using Cross-Layer Techniques for Communication Systems, USA, IGI Global, 2012, pp. 94-119.

Reference I

Dr. Sudip Misra

Associate Professor

Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur Kharagpur, West Bengal, India, 721302.

E-mail: sudipm@iitkgp.ac.in, Phone: +91 9734880277

Dr. K. Sreenivasa Rao

Associate Professor

Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur Kharagpur, West Bengal, India, 721302.

E-mail: ksrao@sit.iitkgp.ernet.in, Phone: +91 3222 282336

Mr. Sumit Goswami

(E-mail: sumit@hqr.drdo.in, Phone: +91 11 23007424)

Additional Director, Dte of MIST,

Defence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO) H.Q., Rajaji Marg, New Delhi, India, 110011.

Dr. Ngai-Man (Man) Cheung

Assistant Professor

Information Systems Technology and Design Singapore University of Technology and Design

8 Somapah Road, Singapore, 487372.

E-mail: ngaiman_cheung@sutd.edu.sg, Phone: +65 6499 4542